Top, top, top. We start right after the משנה Mishnah on יט
עמוד ב. Yud Tet Amud Bet. We're continuing to discuss the act
of שחיטה, shechita, the location of it. The משנה Mishnah on יט
עמוד ב Yud Tet Amud Bet contrasts it to the act of
מליקה. melika. מליקה Melika is only valid from the back of the
neck, שחיטה shechita is valid anywhere the throat, which is the front
of the throat and the sides. The basic reason being that there's
really not a specific place for שחיטה, shechita, well there is in
terms of the trachea and the esophagus, but not in terms of
the of the throat, it's just that if you go from the
back, you break the backbone and the spinal cord and you make
the animal a טריפה treifa as opposed to מליקה melika where specifically
it has to be done from the back. So we pick up
now with the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, יט עמוד
ב Yud Tet Amud Bet at where the גמרא Gemara begins, about
ten lines from the bottom. מאי עורף, Mai oref, where does it
mean the עורף, oref, which is where the משנה Mishnah says you
do the מליקה melika from? אילימא עורף ממש, Ileima oref mamash, so
if you say it literally means the עורף, oref, the עורף oref
here does not mean is understood by the גמרא Gemara not to
mean the back of the neck, but actually mean the back of
the head. So if you say literally it means
עורף, oref, skull? Yeah, like you know this area, or not the
whole skull, the area at the back of your head, like you
know back or like you know here.
So, I don't know if we have a text, we have a
specific term for that, but okay. מאי איריא שוחט, Mai irya shocheit,
why is only שחיטה shechita not good? אפילו מולק נמי, Afilu moleik
nami, even מולק moleik is not good. How
do why? Because ממול ערפו אמר רחמנא, Mimul orpo amar rachmana, opposite
the עורף, oref, and not the עורף oref itself. אלא מאי עורף,
Ela mai oref, so what does the משנה Mishnah mean when it
says the עורף? oref? ממול עורף, Mimul oref, it means opposite the
עורף, oref, right, it's using the term loosely, it means the back
of the neck, it does not mean the back of the head.
כדקתני סיפא, Kidekatani seifa,
like the end of it says, כל העורף כשר למליקה. kol ha-oref
kasher le-melika. So the entire עורף oref is כשר kasher for מליקה.
melika. How do you get anything out of that? Because the entire
means that it's a length, and if it just meant the back
of the head, apparently it means like just this small area at
the back of the head right before the neck begins, so you
wouldn't say the entire length of it because it wouldn't have a
length, it would just be like a more limited small location. Alright,
anyway the עורף oref means the actual back of the neck, it
does not mean the back of the head in the משנה. Mishnah.
What is that פסוק? pasuk? What is it talking about?
Oh. That's
about how you do the מליקה. melika. It says ממול ערפו ולא
יבדיל, mimul orpo velo yavdil, yeah it says ומלקו ממול ערפו, u-malako
mimul orpo, you do מליקה melika from
what particular thing is it?
It's I forget if it's the עולה olah or the חטאת, chatas,
but it's the bird that you do the bird קרבן, korban, right.
It's the exact thing that the משנה Mishnah is talking about that
you do how you bring a bird קרבן korban is that you
separate it from the back of its head. You know you slaughter
it from the back of its neck. Okay but עורף oref here
is understood to mean not the neck itself or the back of
the neck but the back of the head, so ממול עורף mimul
oref is the actual back of the neck. מנא הני מילי, Minani
mili, how do you know that that's the location? דתנו רבנן Detano
rabbanan we taught ממול ערפו, mimul orpo, opposite the עורף, oref, מול
הרואה את העורף, mul ha-ro'eh es ha-oref, opposite what sees the עורף,
oref, meaning the thing that is not opposite in terms of like
you know this is the back and this is the front, not
that opposite but sort of facing the עורף. oref. So if this
is the עורף, oref, opposite or facing the עורף oref is the
area a little bit lower down, the back of the neck. Okay,
וכן הוא אומר ve-chein hu omeir and it says similarly והוא יושב
ממולי, ve-hu yosheiv mimuli, he is standing opposite me. So opposite there
means like facing, right, if somebody is opposite you, they're facing you.
So if the עורף oref is the lower back of the head,
then the ממול עורף mimul oref is the back of the neck,
is the place immediately next to it but in a way facing
it. All right, ואומר ve-omeir and the verse says, and this is
where we know what עורף oref itself means, כי פנו אלי עורף
ולא פנים. ki fanu eilai oref velo fanim. They turned to me
their עורף oref and not their face. מאי ואומר, Mai ve-omeir, what
does it mean and it says? וכי תימא עורף גופיה לא ידנא
היכא, Ve-chi teima oref gufei lo yadnan heicha, we don't know what
the עורף oref itself is, where it is, דנדע מול דידיה היכא,
de-neida mul didei heicha, that we should know what opposite the עורף
oref means? תא שמע, Ta shema, so the verse says, כי פנו
אלי עורף ולא פנים. ki fanu eilai oref velo fanim. They turned
to me their עורף oref not their face. מכלל דעורף להדי פנים,
Miklal de-oref la-hadei fanim, so you see that the עורף oref is
directly opposite the face. So if this is the face, the עורף
oref is the back of the head and opposite the face, then
the ממול עורף mimul oref is the back of the neck, is
this area down here. Of course this raises questions
like your front and עורף oref is your back, doesn't it could
be.
Could be. Okay, that's true, could be. Anyway it is interesting also
if you think about obviously the classic phrase of עם קשה עורף,
am keshei oref, right, like you talk about a stiff-necked people. So
if the עורף oref itself is the back of the head, not
the neck, what does it mean to have a stiff back of
the head? I mean a stiff neck is you don't turn it,
right, you don't do תשובה teshuvah or something, what does it mean
to have a עם קשה עורף am keshei oref in terms of
the back of the head? I really don't know. Okay, now that
we're done determining what the עורף oref is, we go into look
at we start analyzing the halakhic aspects here. אמרי בני רבי חייא.
Amari benei rabbi chiya. The sons of רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya said,
which were יהודה Yehuda and חזקיה. Chizkiya. So the sons of רבי
חייא Rabbi Chiya said the following: מצוות מליקה, Mitzvos melika, how do
you do מליקה? melika? מחזיר סימנים אחורי העורף ומולק. Machazir simanim achorei
haoref umolayk.
So he wants you to do מליקה melika also without first severing
the spinal cord, the backbone. Because as we know, that's why you
can't do שחיטה shechita from the back because it makes the animal
a טריפה treifa first. So he's concerned even by מליקה. melika. And
even though מליקה melika is supposed to be in the back, he
says you somehow move within the animal's throat, the trachea and the
esophagus, to behind the spinal cord, right? And you do the מליקה
melika from the back, but you cut the trachea and the esophagus
before you get to the spinal cord.
All entirely according to him?
Yeah. That's what he says. Well, I guess it's true that for
עולה olah you wouldn't have to cut both, you'd only have to
cut one, but for a חטאת, chatas, you have to really cut
both, so, what?
And that's why you use your hand as a tool to manipulate,
maybe, could be.
Okay, so that's what they say. But איכא דאמרי, ika de'amrei,
now some of read him say אף מחזיר, af machazir, that even
that is acceptable, but it's not what you have to do. ואיכא
דאמרי, ve'ika de'amrei, others say מחזיר דווקא. machazir davka. No, according to
the sons of רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya, you have to do that
in order to prevent you from making the animal a טריפה treifa
presumably. ומסתברא כמאן דאמר אף מחזיר. umistabra keman de'amar af machazir.
It makes sense that we're talking that you even do that, but
not that you have to do that. ממאי, mimmai, how do you
know? מדיתני, miditni, our משנה mishna says השוחט מן העורף שחיטתו פסולה.
hashocheit min haoref shechitasa pesula. That if you שחט shecht from the
back of the neck, the שחיטה shechita is not good. והמולק מן
העורף מליקתו כשרה, vehamolayk min haoref melikasa kesheira, if you do the
מליקה melika from there it's valid. דף כ' עמוד א'. daf chaf
amud aleph. ואי סלקא דעתך מחזיר דווקא, ve'isalka deitach machazir davka,
and if the only way you could do מליקה melika is by
bringing the trachea and the esophagus to the back of the neck,
so when it says you do עורף oref from the back, it
means with the trachea and the esophagus in front of the spinal
cord,
so if that's the only way מליקה melika is good, מאי איריא
מולק? mai irya molayk? Why is only מליקה melika good from the
back of the neck? אפילו שוחט נמי. afillu shocheit nami. שחיטה shechita
should also be good because the גמרא gemara takes for granted that
there is no specific place where שחיטה shechita is, you know, limited.
I mean, as I said, in the trachea and the esophagus it
has to cut within a certain space, but there's no logical reason
why שחיטה shechita can't be from the back. The only reason שחיטה
shechita can't be from the back is because then you will break
the backbone and the, you know, spinal cord before you get to
the trachea and esophagus, you'll make it a טריפה treifa first. So
the גמרא gemara says if that's—but if מליקה melika is by bringing
the trachea and esophagus so that you encounter them before the backbone,
then שחיטה shechita should be just as valid from the back. And
if the משנה mishna says you can't do שחיטה shechita from the
back, it must be assuming because you do not, or don't at
least have to, bring the trachea and the esophagus, you know, in
front of the backbone. אלא לאו שמע מינה? ella lav shema mina?
מליקה melika is only used in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, only
for birds that are then קרבנות.
korbanos.
The עולה olah is not eaten, the חטאת chatas is eaten. So
yes, so part of the חידוש, chiddush, right, it's important they be
כשר, kasher, A because the חטאת chatas is eaten and B because
of the general principle, you know, that we don't, you know, we
don't allow on the מזבח mizbe'ach something that's not כשר. kasher. However,
you are correct in that if somebody were to, you know, the
גמרא gemara deals with a case of let's say for some reason
the קרבן korban is פסול, pasul, then this is no longer recognized
as a legitimate act of שחיטה. shechita. It's only recognized as an
act of שחיטה shechita in the context of it being a
קרבן.
korban. But yes, outside the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash is a נבילה,
neveila, right?
It's a טריפה treifa or a נבילה, neveila, correct, it's totally פסול.
pasul. So only in the context of a bird קרבן korban is
this recognized as a valid שחיטה. shechita.
Okay, yes, that takes your point about
the backbone being a טריפה. treifa. What? To be כשר kasher if
you pull the סימנים simanim to the back?
Well, that's the question. That's the גמרא's gemara question. Why do we
have to say that only מליקה melika is good from the back
and not שחיטה shechita if you're pulling these סימנים? simanim? Right, what
you're saying is that in general we assume that מליקה, melika, right,
that's a variation of the question, which is in general we assume
that מליקה, melika, if it weren't a קרבן, korban, would be a
נבילה. neveila. Why do we assume that if you're bringing the סימנים
simanim to the back? It's a variation of the גמרא's gemara question.
Why are we only assuming מליקה melika is valid? שחיטה shechita should
also be valid if you're pulling the סימנים simanim to the back.
Yes? Okay, James, do you have a question?
I was going to suggest that the answer to the question they're
asking now I would think because large animals you can't pull
the—yes, but it doesn't matter. Oh, you mean you're saying maybe we're
just saying we're comparing, but then we're not comparing מליקה melika to
שחיטה, shechita, we're comparing sort of like מליקה melika to שחיטת בהמה.
shechitas beheima. The משנה mishna seems to be a very general statement
of all שחיטה. shechita. So let's take a look. אלא לאו שמע
מינה, ella lav shema mina, it must be we see from this,
אף מחזיר, af machazir, that you don't—even if we accept what בני
רבי חייא bnei Rabbi Chiya say that it's valid for מליקה, melika,
it doesn't mean it's the only way to do it. It means
you could even do that. So since you could even do that,
ומתניתין בלא החזיר, umasnisa belo hechizir, and our משנה mishna we'd be
talking about a standard case where you did not move the סימנים
simanim to the back, and in that type of a standard case,
it's only good for מליקה, melika, not for שחיטה. shechita. But there
is no way of claiming that you need to do it by
מליקה melika because if that were true, it would be just as
good for שחיטה. shechita.
Well, it says מצוות מליקה. mitzvas melika. Yeah, it makes it seem
like that's what you really should be doing. I understand.
We're trying to salvage their statement though. Okay, so it's a way
of doing it.
So it's a way of doing the מצוה mitzvah of שחיטה. shechita.
I understand, we're trying to at least salvage their statement based on
these very reasonable arguments. So אמר רב ינאי, amar Rav Yannai, רב
ינאי Rav Yannai doesn't even like this. So here's what רב ינאי
Rav Yannai says: יקבלו הרובים את תשובתן. yekablu haRubim et teshuvatan. So
here the רובים, Rubim, does that mean the word רוב? rov? But
it means like רביא, revia, which is like an Aramaic word for
like children or, you know, young people, young person. So says, let
the kids take get their response, you know. So it's the בני
רבי חייא.
Bnei
Rabbi Chiya.
He did not like their position and he's coming to, you know,
to respond to it, to reject it. So he says, listen up
kids, I got an answer for you. Okay, be prepared to accept,
you know, this answer. דתניא, detanya, here's what
our, here's our משנה, Mishnah, the end of our משנה: Mishnah: נמצא
כשר בשחיטה פסול במליקה כשר במליקה פסול בשחיטה. nimtza kasher bishchita pasul
bimelika kasher bimelika pasul bishchita. Our משנה Mishnah said what's good for
שחיטה shechita is not good for מליקה. melika. The simple sense of
the משנה Mishnah was it was a way of summing up what
came before, meaning the front of the throat and the sides are
good for שחיטה, shechita, they're not good for מליקה. melika. What's good
for מליקה, melika, the back of the neck, פסול בשחיטה, pasul bishchita,
it's not good for שחיטה. shechita. So simply that is just summing
up what came before. But obviously the גמרא Gemara never likes the
idea that it's just summarizing and restating, so assumes that it's coming
to say, extend it to other cases as well, that what's כשר
בשחיטה kasher bishchita is not good for מליקה melika and vice versa.
It's a general statement, not just to sum up what came before.
So לאתויי מאי? l'atuyei mai? What is it coming to say works
for one and doesn't work for the other? לאו לאתויי, lav l'atuyei,
it must be coming to the case of מחזיר סימנים לאחורי העורף,
machzir simanim leachorei haoref, that if you were to bring the סימנים
simanim to the back of the neck, so that would be good
for שחיטה. shechita. The גמרא Gemara takes it as axiomatic that that's
going to be good for שחיטה. shechita. Why not? You cut the
trachea and the esophagus, who cares whether you did it from the
front or the back as long as you didn't hit the spinal
cord first. So that will be good for שחיטה. shechita. And the
משנה Mishnah is saying what's good for שחיטה shechita is not good
for מליקה. melika. So he's not even willing to accept that this
is also, that this is not only that it's not required by
מליקה, melika, he's not even willing to accept that it's acceptable by
מליקה, melika, because our משנה Mishnah says if it works for שחיטה,
shechita, it doesn't work for מליקה. melika. And the גמרא Gemara takes
it for granted that this works for שחיטה, shechita, bringing the trachea
and the esophagus to the back. So therefore by definition it does
not work by מליקה. melika. Okay, which also feeds in, you know,
to as Michael was indicating before, our general assumption that מליקה melika
is something that in all other circumstances would make the animal like
a נבילה, neveila, would never be a כשר שחיטה. kasher shechita. And
according to רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya, you could have a case where
מליקה melika could have been a כשר שחיטה kasher shechita if you
brought the סימנים simanim to the back. Okay, so that's his response.
So is it not coming to say that that case is not
a good מליקה? melika? So
אמר רבה בר בר חנה, amar Rabbah bar bar Chana, לא, lo,
not necessarily. לאתויי, l'atuyei, maybe here's what it's coming to exclude: לאתויי
שן וצפורן, l'atuyei shen vetzipporen,
which of course is a totally different direction, not about the issues
of the throat and where you're doing the שחיטה, shechita, but what
you're using, the tools. You're using a שן shen and a צפורן,
tzipporen, a tooth and a fingernail. So meaning, now what does it
mean a tooth and a fingernail? So רש"י Rashi says, one minute
let me just double check רש"י Rashi again,
one minute, I know, I know, I know.
Right, that what is
good by מליקה, melika, what's good by מליקה melika is using your
fingernail. That's what you would use is your fingernail. So what's good
by מליקה melika is not good by שחיטה. shechita. You cannot use
your fingernail while it's attached to your hand for שחיטה shechita because
if you remember what we said before, that things that are מחובר
mechubar according to רבי, Rabbi, they're attached to the ground or part
of a person or part of an animal cannot be used for
שחיטה. shechita. So what you can use for מליקה, melika, which is
your fingernail, well, okay, I'll get to that in a second, you
cannot use an attached fingernail for שחיטה. shechita. Maybe that's what it's
coming to say, not the where in the neck and the throat
or whatever, but what tool you're using. So number one, that's a
little bizarre, the simple sense of the משנה Mishnah is of course
talking about the issues about the throat and the neck, not going
back to issues about the instrument used. The other problem with this
is what Michael says, why does it throw in the word שן
shen here? So it could just be that that, you know, that
these are like a package. When the גמרא Gemara before talks about,
you know, can you use a שן shen or a צפורן, tzipporen,
it talked about them together but what we really mean here is
just the fingernail. You can use the fingernail for מליקה melika when
it's attached to your thumb, but you cannot use an attached fingernail
for שחיטה. shechita. However, תוספות Tosafot suggests, believe it or not, gesundheit,
to take the word שן shen literally and to say, how do
we know that you use your fingernail? Because the גמרא Gemara learns
it because it says from the פסוק, pasuk, it says that the
כהן Kohen does מליקה, melika, ומלקו, umalako, it says, I forget exactly
the פסוק, pasuk, but it speaks about the כהן Kohen and the
דרשה drasha is בעצמו של כהן, be'atzmo shel Kohen, the מליקה melika
has to be done with the person of the כהן Kohen himself.
So תוספות Tosafot says, well, maybe also his שן! shen! And maybe
if a כהן Kohen is able to sharpen his שן shen and
use his שן, shen, and the only question תוספות Tosafot has about
doing מליקה melika with your שן shen is, don't you need to
use your right? Right, because all the things that the כהן Kohen
does has to be with his right hand. So how do you
do the right with your שן? shen? It's not like a right
and left. תוספות, Tosafot, well, maybe if it's a part of the
body that doesn't have a right and a left, you don't need
to use specifically the right. Maybe using the right is only if
it's a part of your body that has a right and a
left. So תוספות Tosafot actually thinks, reads as a possible read of
this גמרא, Gemara, that מליקה melika would be כשר kasher if the
כהן Kohen used his שן, shen, which also feeds in... maybe he
could use his toenail. You know,
once we're saying that, we're not saying specifically that it's a fingernail
now, it's just about a part of his body.
Would we have a problem drinking blood then? Oh. Would it get
somehow in your...
I don't know, spit it out.
Yes, רשי Rashi says שאין מחוברת, she-ein mechuberet, so he includes... he's
not dismissing...
yeah,
but he's talking about... no, the... he's saying that's פסול בשחיטה... passul
bi-shechita... so, I have...
no, but then when it gets
to כשר במליקה...
kasher bi-melika...
no, no, because if you continue to read רשי, Rashi, רשי Rashi
says והכי קאמר, ve-hachi ka-amar, כשר במליקה כגון ציפורן מחוברת, kasher bi-melika
kegon tziporen mechuberet, פסול בשחיטה. passul bi-shechita.
So when it gets to כשר במליקה, kasher bi-melika, רשי Rashi only
mentions the fingernail.
But it says כגון. kegon.
Yeah, but that's what's invalid for שחיטה shechita includes the tooth, but
what's valid for מליקה...
melika... I understand, but he's including שן.
shen.
Maybe, maybe not. It's very often things come... the גמרא Gemara refers
to these things in packages. Anyway, I think רשי Rashi is saying
just the fingernail. But תוספות Tosafot certainly is willing to read the
גמרא Gemara literally and suggesting that the כהן Kohen could even use
his tooth for מליקה. melika. So, right. So anyway, so maybe that's
what the משנה Mishna is to our... it does, yes. Why do
you have to bite?
Can you use your fingernail?
Because you're like biting into it...
it's אבר מן החי.
ever
min ha-chai.
It's not אבר מן החי. ever min ha-chai. You'd have to...
you'd have to cut it with your teeth.
No, no, no, actually we're going to see that. מליקה Melika as
opposed to שחיטה, shechita, and this is another reason why מליקה melika
is not as good as שחיטה, shechita, not just where it is,
is that מליקה melika is piercing, where שחיטה shechita is cutting. So
you could actually... you need sharp, right.
But piercing means you bite into it.
Yeah, you could actually bite with sharp teeth. Yeah. Okay, so back
to the גמרא, Gemara, fine. Back to the גמרא. Gemara. אמר רבא
בר חנה לאו, Amar Rava bar Chana lav, למעוטי שן וציפורן. lema'utei
shen ve-tziporen. Maybe we're only coming to exclude the tooth and the
fingernail, that those are good for מליקה, melika, at least the fingernail,
if not also the tooth, and not good for שחיטה. shechita. So
the גמרא Gemara says שן וציפורן בהדיא קתני להו. shen ve-tziporen be-hedya
katani le-hu. No, that's explicit in the previous משנה, Mishna, you know,
that it's not good for שחיטה. shechita. You wouldn't need this משנה
Mishna to teach it.
And anyway, does it say it's good for מליקה melika or not?
We don't know. I mean, presumably that presumption hasn't changed. It depends
how you read that גמרא Gemara about the tooth. אלא, Ella, so
and again, it's bizarre that that's what our משנה Mishna is talking
about. Our משנה Mishna seems to be focusing on where in the
animal. אלא אמר רבי ירמיה, Ella amar Rabbi Yirmiya, למעוטי מוליך ומביא.
lema'utei moliche u-mevi. So this is exactly the issue before about how
do you do the מליקה. melika. By שחיטה shechita you do it
by מוליך ומביא, moliche u-mevi, moving back and forth, by a, you
know, horizontal motion. By מליקה melika you do it by a cutting,
piercing motion. That would totally be פסול passul by, you know, שחיטה,
shechita, that would be called by הדרסה, hadrassa, you know, pressure, would
not be the simple cutting.
You have to have sharp הדרסה. hadrassa.
Right, right, you have to really sharpen the edges of your fingernail.
Okay, so anyway, so it's saying that that is, that is כשר
kasher for שחיטה, shechita, פסול passul for מליקה, melika, and the reverse,
what's כשר kasher for מליקה, melika, the piercing, is פסול passul for
שחיטה. shechita. So that's... I mean that's what it's talking about. And
therefore it's not talking about this issue about bringing the סימנים simanim
to the back. So the גמרא Gemara says הניחא למאן דאמר מוליך
ומביא במליקה פסול. henicha le-man de-amar moliche u-mevi bi-melika passul. That's good
if you say that the horizontal motion, the back and forth, is
invalid for מליקה. melika. Then it's saying what's כשר kasher for שחיטה,
shechita, the back and forth motion, is invalid for מליקה melika and
vice versa, piercing which is כשר kasher for מליקה melika is פסול
passul for שחיטה. shechita. אלא למאן דאמר כשר, Ella le-man de-amar kasher,
but if you say that that actually is acceptable for מליקה, melika,
the back and forth motion, מאי איכא למימר? mai ika le-meimar? That
cannot be the read of our משנה. Mishna. And then it goes
back to the read of our משנה Mishna must be coming to
say to exclude the case of moving the סימנים simanim to the
back. So the גמרא Gemara says okay, בני רבי חייא סברי לה
כמאן דאמר מוליך ומביא במליקה פסול. benei Rabbi Chiya savrei lah ke-man
de-amar moliche u-mevi bi-melika passul. They would hold like the words in
it says that, yes, going back and forth is not good for
מליקה. melika. So therefore when the משנה Mishna says that what's good
for שחיטה shechita is not good for מליקה, melika, it's not... it's
not referring to the bring of the סימנים simanim in the back,
it's referring to this back and forth motion. So where are we
with this? Number one is we introduced this bizarre idea that you
could possibly do מליקה melika with your teeth, the way תוספות Tosafot
reads the גמרא. Gemara. Number two is we've now seen that there
are two major differences, which is not in our משנה, Mishna, about
why a מליקה melika is not a good שחיטה. shechita. One it's
from the back and it breaks the spinal cord. The other is
that we're now emphasizing is that it is not the cutting motion,
it is the piercing motion. And that's exactly what is good for
מליקה, melika, not good for שחיטה. shechita. Can you also do the
cutting motion for מליקה? melika? Would that also be accepted? That's debated.
Can you do the סימנים simanim in the back for מליקה? melika?
That's also debated. So if you say yes to both of those,
I should say a מליקה melika could be כשר שחיטה. kasher shechita.
If you move the סימנים simanim in the back and you do
the cutting motion. But right now the גמרא Gemara is treating it
as an either-or. Maybe you can bring the סימנים simanim in the
back, that's what בני רבי חייא benei Rabbi Chiya says, although the
גמרא Gemara is resisting that, but then they're saying בני רבי חייא
benei Rabbi Chiya would say you have to do a piercing motion.
Maybe you could do a cutting motion, but you can't bring the
סימנים simanim in the back. So it's interesting to note that either
approach the גמרא Gemara is taking, it does not have that the
מליקה melika would be כשר. kasher. Either because it refuses to accept
that you could bring the סימנים simanim in the back, or because
it refuses to accept that you could do a cutting motion for
מליקה melika and insists on a piercing motion. Okay, so these are
the series of differences between מליקה melika and שחיטה. shechita.
So the conclusion is really is, and generally, that's what מליקה... melika...
מליקה melika really is just...
general מליקה melika is back and no סימנים. simanim. Don't move the
סימנים, simanim, go from the back and do piercing, so two ways
in which it's different from שחיטה. shechitah. It breaks the backbone before
it gets to the סימנים, simanim, which by שחיטה shechitah would make
it a טרפה treifah or a נבילה, neveilah, and it's a- it's
a piercing motion, not a cutting motion. And the only question is:
would, can you change one of those variables as long as you
leave, continue to do it from the back?
And use your fingernail.
And use your fingernail, but that- oh right, and according to רבי,
Rebbi, thank you. According to רבי, Rebbi, that's a debate. Can you
use an attached fingernail for שחיטה? shechitah? That's a good point. According
to רבי Rebbi you cannot, according to רבי חייא Rebbi Chiyya you
can. Yes.
Do you have an insight as to whether or not this is
just because מליקה melikah is separate, or if it's on a spectrum
from fish to בהמה beheimah and עוף of is in the middle?
That's interesting. That idea of spectrum is definitely used by the גמרא
Gemara to explain why you only need to cut one סימן siman
in an עוף, of, why you don't need to cut two סימנים.
simanim. Is that a way to explain why the תורה Torah would
allow a totally different approach when it comes to, you know, the
קדשים? kodashim? Maybe. I
mean, the גמרא Gemara does believe, there is a position in the
גמרא Gemara that biblically you don't need to do any שחיטה shechitah
by a bird. So according to that position, you know, that would
certainly make this much more understandable because then biblically you don't need
to do a שחיטה, shechitah, so it's totally okay.
Yeah, but I don't have- beyond that, I don't have a good
theory about this bizarre thing why this is acceptable. Right, well that-
but his question is: why of all things do we make this
difference by birds? Right. It's a very good question, I really- I
really don't know. Okay, so now let's continue the גמרא. Gemara. אמר
רב כהנא: Amar Rav Kahana: מצות מליקה, Mitzvat melikah, here's how you
do מליקה: melikah: קוצץ ויורד. kotzetz veyored. So now we are emphasizing
again that it's this piercing. You cut as you descend, meaning you
pierce. It's not a- it's not a horizontal cut. זו היא מצותן.
Zu hi mitzvatan. This is the way to do it. סבר רב
אמי למימר: Sevar Rav Ami lemeimar: קוצץ ויורד kotzetz veyored אין, in,
so רב אמי Rav Ami assumed that what he meant- what רב
כהנא Rav Kahana meant was: you can only do a cutting and
going down, a piercing. מוליך ומביא molic vemeivi לא, lo, you cannot
do a horizontal cut. אמר ליה רבי ירמיה: Amar lei Rabbi Yirmeya:
No, כל שכן דמוליך ומביא במליקה כשר. Kol shekein demolic vemeivi bemelikah
kasher. No, certainly that should be good. Which is bizarre. Why certainly?
So far now it's been the diametric opposite of שחיטה, shechitah, but
all of a sudden for this he assumes no reason that that
should make it worse if you're just- you're doing a normal שחיטה
shechitah type of a cut. ומה זו היא מצותה? U'mah zu hi
mitzvatah? What does it mean "this is the מצוה"? mitzvah אימה אף
זו היא מצותה. Eima af zu hi mitzvatah. Even this is the
מצוה. mitzvah. So that's a- right, questionable, a reframing of the earlier
question. So the same way there was one question "can you move
the סימנים simanim in the back and make it something that would
be better for שחיטה?", shechitah? here's the question also: "can you do
a horizontal cut which would also make it better for שחיטה?". shechitah?
Okay, now we are going to, you know, continue again with this
theme. Let's take a look. אמר רבי ירמיה אמר שמואל: Amar Rabbi
Yirmeya amar Shmuel: כל הכשר בשחיטה, Kol hakasher beshchitah, anything that's good
for שחיטה, shechitah, כנגדו בעורף כשר במליקה. kenegdo ba'oref kasher bemelikah. If
you do the- if opposite that in the back of the neck
is good for מליקה. melikah. Now what is he coming to include?
Anything כשר kasher for שחיטה shechitah is כשר kasher for מליקה. melikah.
Like it doesn't mean using a knife, it doesn't mean doing necessarily
מוליך ומביא. molic vemeivi. So again, the emphasis here is not on
the act, although the גמרא Gemara tries to move it in that
direction. The emphasis here is sort of in the location of the
animal's throat, the neck or whatever. So he's saying wherever it's כשר
kasher from the throat by שחיטה, shechitah, it's כשר kasher from the
back of the neck by מליקה. melikah. So what is this coming
to say? So the גמרא Gemara says here's how the גמרא Gemara
understands its implications: הפסול בשחיטה פסול במליקה. Hapasul beshchitah pasul bemelikah. It
suggests that what's not good for שחיטה shechitah is not good for
מליקה. melikah. למעוטי מאי? Lema'utei mai? What is this excluding? אילימא למעוטי
עיקור סימנים, Eilima lema'utei ikur simanim, uprooting the סימנים. simanim. Now what
does עיקור סימנים ikur simanim mean? One of the פסולי שחיטה psulei
shechitah is עיקור, ikur, the uprooted סימן. siman. Now רש"י Rashi in
a few places- which means basically, I- again, it sounds like what
we sort of said before, moving it around. Somehow you tear the
trachea or the esophagus out of where it's sort of like embedded
in the flesh and in the throat inside of the animal. So
you move it from its place. You yank it, you move it
from its place. Although interestingly the גמרא Gemara never sort of assumes-
associates that with what we were talking before about מחזיר סימנים. machzir
simanim. So I think it doesn't just mean that you sort of,
you know, move it relative to the spinal cord, but you somehow
actually, you know, remove it out of where it's embedded in the
flesh of the- of the- of the throat. I'm- I'm sorry, I
am not a doctor, so I can't give you greater specificity. Anyway,
what's the problem? רש"י Rashi in a few places says that makes
the animal a טרפה. treifah. תוספות Tosafot very cogently argues that we've
never seen this as an issue of טרפה, treifah, we've only seen
it as an issue of שחיטה. shechitah. And we have to assume
that the animal is not a טרפה, treifah, it's just a פסול
שחיטה. psul shechitah. For שחיטה shechitah to be כשר, kasher, it requires
that the trachea and esophagus be in their sort of embedded natural
location in the throat of the animal. Okay, so now we're saying
what's פסול pasul for שחיטה shechitah is פסול pasul for מליקה. melikah.
What are we trying to say? So he says maybe we mean
this problem of עיקור סימנים. ikur simanim. We know עיקור סימנים ikur
simanim is a פסול שחיטה. psul shechitah. Is it a פסול מליקה?
psul melikah? If the trachea and the esophagus have been, you know,
somehow ripped from their location in the throat of an animal, not
torn themselves, but, you know, detached, will this invalidate a מליקה melikah
the same way it invalidates a שחיטה? shechitah? That's what we're trying
to assume maybe is what שמואל Shmuel means. So let's take a
look.
So, למיעוטי מאי? limutei mai? אילימא למיעוטי עיקר סימנים ileima limutei ikkar
simanim when the סימנים simanim are uprooted? So, והתניא רמי בר יחזקאל,
vehatanya Rami bar Yechezkel, ברייתא רמי בר יחזקאל Baraita Rami bar Yechezkel
teaches אין עיקר סימנים בעוף, ein ikkar simanim ba'of, that this is
not a problem by birds. So there you go, David, similar to
the point you were making before, that in general we're more lenient
by birds. So the same way we're more lenient that you only
have to cut one סימן, siman, we're also more lenient that the
עיקר סימנים ikkar simanim is not a פסול שחיטה psul shechita by
birds. So you can't say that he's coming to say what's invalid
for שחיטה shechita is invalid for מליקה, melika, because if we're dealing
with birds, it isn't even invalid for שחיטה. shechita. עיקר סימנים ikkar
simanim is not a problem. So אמר רב פפא, amar Rav Pappa,
so here's what it's coming to do: למיעוטי ראשו, limutei rosho, the
head. So the same way you can't do שחיטה shechita from the
head, you also can't do שחיטה shechita from the back of the
neck in the head area. So the גמרא Gemara says פשיטא! peshita!
ראשו, rosho, the head? פשיטא, peshita, obviously! ממול עורף אמר רחמנא, mimul
oreph amar Rachmana, it says opposite the עורף. oreph. The עורף oreph
we said is the back of the head, and opposite that is
the back of the neck, ולא בראשו, velo verosho, and not the
head itself. So the גמרא Gemara says okay, but מאי ראשו, mai
rosho, what do we mean to exclude the head? שיפוי ראשו, shipuy
rosho, it is the sort of the
slope of the head, היכי דנקט משיפוי ראשו והתים ואזיל עד דמטא
לתתאי.
heichi denakat
meshipuy rosho vehitim ve'azil ad demata letattai. So what we're talking about
is we can't leave up what we did yesterday. You start too
high, you're doing this from the back, whether you do it from
the back or the front, right, you start too high and you
end either way,
but if you're doing מליקה, melika, you start like at the slope,
which is too high, and then in the end, you end in
the right place. So that's not good, the same way it's not
good by שחיטה, shechita, this issue of הגרמה, hagrama, starting in the
wrong place and ending in the wrong place, it's also not good
by מליקה. melika.
Okay, כי אתא רב הונא אמר רב
אסי,
ki ata Rav Huna amar
Rav
Assi, דאמר רב הונא אמר רב אסי, de'amar Rav Huna amar Rav
Assi,
like we taught yesterday, הגרים שליש, higrim shelish, there you go, if
you start too high even if it's only the beginning third, ושחט
שני שלישים, veshachat shenei shelishim, and you do the last two thirds,
פסולה, psula, it's invalid. So maybe that's what we're coming to say,
it is a פסול הגרמה psul hagrama by מליקה. melika. אמר ליה
רב אחא בריה דרבא לרב אשי, amar lei Rav Acha bereih deRava
leRav Ashi, so רב אחא בריה דרבא Rav Acha bereih deRava said
back to רב אשי, Rav Ashi, הא דתני רמי בר יחזקאל, ha
detani Rami bar Yechezkel, אין עיקר סימנים בעוף. ein ikkar simanim ba'of.
So now we're back, I'm sorry, that's fine, that's what שמואל Shmuel
meant. Now we're back to this question about עיקר. ikkar. This statement
that עיקר ikkar is not a problem by birds, when the trachea
and esophagus are not sort of in their right place, לא אמרן
אלא למאן דאמר אין שחיטה לעוף מן התורה. lo amaran ela leman
de'amar ein shechita la'of min haTorah. There you go again, David, just
as you were talking. That works if you say that we basically
have a fundamental different approach to birds. By birds, there's no real
שחיטה shechita requirement. So therefore, obviously, I mean it's almost sort of
a tautology. If there's no שחיטה shechita requirement, of course there's no
problem about עיקר סימנים, ikkar simanim, because there's no real biblical requirement
about birds.
But the point presumably you said before about עוף, oph, you said
the תורה Torah spoke about it.
Yes, that's how you do מליקה, melika, but שחיטה shechita would not
have any specific requirement. Okay, now the point seems to be maybe
more than that, not just there's no biblical problem of עיקר סימנים,
ikkar simanim, but there's no rabbinic problem either. That since, if the
whole idea of שחיטה shechita by birds is rabbinic, then we could
maybe have gone easier on the requirement of עיקר ikkar and say
if the trachea and esophagus are in the wrong place. But for
שחיטה. shechita. The statement was אין עיקר סימנים, ein ikkar simanim, had
nothing to do with מליקה. melika. There's no problem in this time
of עיקר ikkar is not a problem by birds. Okay, that makes
sense if the whole idea of birds is rabbinic, if the whole
שחיטה shechita by birds is rabbinic. אבל, aval, the beginning of כ"ה
ע"ב, Chaf-He Amud Bet, למאן דאמר יש שחיטה לעוף מן התורה, leman
de'amar yesh shechita la'of min haTorah, if there is a biblical requirement
of שחיטה shechita by birds, even if it's only by one סימן,
siman, יש עיקר, yesh ikkar, so then it should stand to reason
that עיקר ikkar would be a similar problem by birds as it
is by animals. אמר ליה, amar lei, he said back to him:
אדרבה, adaraba, the opposite, איפכא מסתברא, ipcha mistabra, the opposite makes sense.
למאן דאמר יש שחיטה לעוף מן התורה, leman de'amar yesh shechita la'of
min haTorah, if it's biblical, the requirement of שחיטה shechita by birds,
איכא למימר דהכי אגמריה, icha lemeimar dehachi agmereih, this maybe is what
משה Moshe was taught by God, דאין עיקר, de'ein ikkar, that there's
no problem, meaning if it's biblical, you're right, it's not parallel, but
you know what, there are other things that aren't parallel. Birds are
one סימן siman and animals are two סימנים. simanim. So okay, if
it's biblical, maybe this is one of the special laws about birds.
There could be differences within each category. This is what God taught
משה, Moshe, that there's no עיקר. ikkar. Now the language of אגמריה,
agmereih, God taught משה, Moshe, which is a very sort of funny,
like משה Moshe is in the בית מדרש Beit Midrash taking notes,
which is sort of what it's, the picture, the picture, the picture
that it evokes is because the whole reason why there's a question
of is there a biblical concept of שחיטה shechita by birds is
because the תורה Torah never uses the word. How did the גמרא
Gemara identify an idea of שחיטה shechita by animals? Try to read
it into the verse. Because it says like וזבחת vezavachta or ושחטת,
veshachata, וזבחת, vezavachta, but basically וזבחת. vezavachta. So it says ah, וזבחת,
vezavachta, that means ritual slaughter and that's by animals. Well guess what?
It never says that by birds. Okay? So I mean, actually the
one place you would have expected it to say it, which was
by the covering of the blood, right, because there it mentions birds,
but there it says כי יצוד ציד חיה או עוף אשר יאכל
ושפך את דמו וכסהו בעפר, ki yazud tzeid chaya o oph asher
ye'achel veshaphach et damo vechisahu be'aphar, spill its blood. It doesn't even
speak about slaughtering. So it never mentions the word וזבחת v'zavachta by
birds. So how could you say it's biblical? It's not in a
פסוק. pasuk. So there's one place where it talks about eating birds
and meat where it tries to connect it, but also it might
just say, okay, it's not in a פסוק. pasuk. הלכה למשה מסיני.
Halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai. We have a tradition that God taught Moses this
requirement and that and not that it's in any פסוק. pasuk. So
once sort of that is the framework of how שחיטה shechita is
from the תורה Torah for birds, we use the phrase והכי אגמריה.
v'hachi agmaray. This is what God would have taught Moses. God would
have taught Moses that birds have a different requirement. Only one סימן,
siman, עיקור ikor doesn't matter. We could accept that there are differences
if it's biblical. והכי אגמריה, v'hachi agmaray, this is what God would
have taught Moses, דאין עיקור, d'ein ikor, that there's no עיקור. ikor.
ואפילו למאן דאמר כבהמה, va'afilu l'man d'amar k'beheimah,
so even if we learn the idea of שחיטה shechita by birds
like an animal from a פסוק, pasuk, רש"י Rashi quotes the פסוק
pasuk which is, what is it? זאת תורת הבהמה והעוף. zot torat
habeheimah v'ha'of.
Okay, not a פסוק pasuk that talks about שחיטה shechita at all,
but a פסוק pasuk that links animals to birds. So even if
they're linked by a פסוק, pasuk, nevertheless, the עניין inyan עיקור ikor
לאו lav כבהמה k'beheimah doesn't mean for all things they're equated. Yes,
we learn out שחיטה, shechita, but maybe it has its own laws.
So if it's biblical, I can accept birds have their own laws
and עיקור ikor is not a problem. אלא למאן דאמר אין שחיטה
לעוף מן התורה, ela l'man d'amar ein shechita l'of min haTorah, but
if שחיטה shechita by birds is not biblical, אלא מדברי סופרים, ela
midivrei sofrim, it's only rabbinic. מהיכא גמירי לה, me'heicha gemiri lah, where
would the rabbis have modeled שחיטה shechita from birds after? It wouldn't
have been its own independent category. They would have taken the model
by בהמה beheimah and extended and applied it to birds. So where
would they have learned the idea of שחיטה shechita from? מבהמה, mibeheimah,
they would have taken the model from animals. So כולהו נוסחא כבהמה,
kuleihu nuscha k'beheimah, so it all should have been like birds and
like animals. But yeah, that's true, there still is the obvious problem
that it's one סימן siman and not two סימנים, simanim, but the
point is like, you know, they maybe would have stopped there, but
I don't know. It's yeah. So anyway his point is I'm not
convinced. I understand that there's this position out there that עיקור ikor
is not a problem, but I'm not so convinced to say oh
that's because it's rabbinic. Maybe he really believes that there are different
rules by שחיטה shechita of animals and שחיטה shechita of birds, and
the same way one סימן siman is good even if it's biblical,
also you could say that עיקור ikor is also is equally not
a problem. And maybe it's the opposite that if it's rabbinic, it's
more sort of just exactly patterned after בהמה beheimah than if it
is biblical, which maybe allows it to have more unique characteristics. Yes.
עיקור ikor a naturally occurring phenomenon or that's the way you kill
an animal?
Yeah, רש"י Rashi normally describes it like it was somehow done through
human agency.
That's an interesting question about is there could it if it's naturally
נעקר? ne'ekar? I think the answer is the same. I don't think
it requires to be done by human agency. The phrase is right,
עיקור ikor sounds also very much like it's the act of tearing
it, uprooting it.
Let's see what רש"י Rashi said earlier when it came up first
in the גמרא. Gemara. One minute.
Yeah,
he just quoted a case where actually it was done through human
agency. But given that רש"י Rashi himself says the עיקור ikor problem
is a טרפה treifa problem, I can't see for רש"י Rashi it
being limited to that. And the way תוספות Tosafot describes it as
well, תוספות Tosafot says that even according to the עיטר, Itur, which
is the opinion that he quotes about that it's a problem just
of the act of שחיטה, shechita, he says no, the act of
שחיטה shechita requires that the סימנים simanim be in their place. So
you're right, although the language more sounds like it's a that it's
referring to actually somebody has physically removed it, the way it's described
by רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot would seem not that that wouldn't
matter. Yeah, that as once they are not in their right place,
it's not a legitimate act of שחיטה. shechita. Right. Okay, so now
let's take a look as the גמרא Gemara continues. So that's the
possibility that עיקור ikor is not a problem at all by birds.
So אמר רבינא אמר לי רבין בר קיסי. amar Ravina amar li
Ravin bar Kisi. So רבין Ravin בר bar קיסי Kisi told to
me, הא דתני רם בר יחזקאל, ha d'tani Ram bar Yechezkel, that
statement of רם Ram בר bar יחזקאל, Yechezkel, אין עיקור סימנים בעוף,
ein ikor simanim b'of, that the uprooting of the סימנים simanim is
not a problem by birds, לא אמרן אלא במליקה. lo amran ela
bimlikah. This is what Michael thought, so now we're saying this according
to one opinion. That's not a general statement. That's about מליקה. mleikah.
מליקה mleikah we know has all these other crazy exceptions. You do
it you break the spinal cord, you do it with the fingernail.
So there too עיקור ikor is not an issue. אבל בשחיטה, aval
bishchita, when it comes to a natural שחיטה, shechita, יש עיקור, yesh
ikor, that is going to be a problem the same way it
is by any
שחיטה. shechita. Okay, so now והאמר רבי ירמיה אמר שמואל כל הכשר
בשחיטה כנגדו בעורף כשר במליקה. v'ha'amar Rabbi Yirmiyah amar Shmuel kol hakesher
bishchita k'negdo ba'oref kasher bimlikah. One minute, the whole way we got
on this conversation was a statement of שמואל Shmuel that what's good
for שחיטה shechita is good for מליקה, mleikah, like sort of like
the opposite of the statement of our משנה. mishnah. So הא פוסלו
פוסלו, ha poslo poslo, so we're trying to infer that there's something
that's a problem by שחיטה, shechita, that's a problem by מליקה. mleikah.
So and you're saying that this type of a thing, עיקור ikor
is a problem by שחיטה, shechita, but it's okay by מליקה. mleikah.
So this goes against שמואל'ס Shmuel's statement. So he says, right, הא
פליגי. ha pligi. Yes, that argues on what I'm saying. Okay, I
don't agree with that statement. Where that's where, that's where we'll have
to just argue about that. So now you have this position which
is עיקור, ikor, right, that we until yesterday we were dealing a
lot with the problem of הגרמה, hagrama, too high. Now we're dealing
with this other פסול שחיטה psul shechita called עיקור, ikor, and we're
saying that it might not be a problem at all by birds,
or maybe it is a problem by birds, but it's not a
problem by מליקה. melika. Now we turn to a new, I mean
obviously related, but a new discussion which is also
very central, I shouldn't say that, which is quoted by some people
in the whole brain death debate. And this gets to the question
about, are we talking about שחיטה shechita when we talk about concepts
like שחיטה shechita and the like? Are these about also defining the
animal as dead, or just defining this as an act of שחיטה?
shechita? I should say before we get into this, one interesting example
of this gap between the two is the גמרא Gemara says that
if you do שחיטה shechita on an animal and the animal is
still thrashing around, right, which it will do after you do שחיטה
shechita for a while, and you take off a piece of meat
and eat it, it's okay because it's now shechted meat and even
though the animal is still thrashing around, it's kosher. However, if a
בן נח Ben Noach were to take off a piece of meat,
what's a בן נח? Ben Noach? בן נח Ben Noach doesn't have
to do שחיטה, shechita, but what's a בן נח Ben Noach אסור
assur in? אבר מן החי. eiver min hachai. For a בן נח
Ben Noach to take off that piece of meat, he would be
חייב chayav for אבר מן החי. eiver min hachai. For a Jew
it's not אבר מן החי eiver min hachai because a Jew has
a halakhic category of שחיטה, shechita, and therefore since you have a
halakhic category of שחיטה, shechita, this is considered to be shechted meat.
But a בן נח Ben Noach doesn't have a halakhic category of
שחיטה, shechita, only has a concept of alive or dead, and from
his perspective the animal is still alive. Now what does that say?
Does that say that from the Jewish perspective the animal is considered
dead once you have a category? And the idea of life and
death anyway is halakhic categories, they don't just describe reality. That's the
whole issue about brain death, right? It's not like there's a physical
reality we're all trying to determine. We're trying to say how does
the law consider where life ends, you know, and where death begins.
So maybe for a Jew the animal is considered dead and for
a non-Jew it's not considered dead, that's one possibility. Or the other
possibility is, you know, is that no, even for the Jew the
animal is alive, but once there's an act of, once שחיטה shechita
is acknowledged, that makes the meat permissible even if the animal is
still considered alive. So I raise this, A, because it really highlights
number one the idea that death is a legal definition, possibly, and
two, that שחיטה shechita and death might not be the same thing.
Okay, so those are important things to think about. Let's see now
what the גמרא Gemara says.
Could you just repeat what you just said?
That brain death may
be under the הלכה Halakha not a physical reality?
No, anybody will tell you it's not just about הלכה. Halakha. Talk
about, you know, when all the discussions in the secular society about
is brain death death, right? It's not like people say, oh, there
is an objective reality, of course there's certain when you
get to
the, yeah, when you get to
a very black and white when nothing in the body is working,
that's clearly the objective reality, any objective reality of death. But in
those gray zones where some things are still functioning and some things
are not, right, it's not like we're all trying to determine this
metaphysical reality of death and we just don't know what equals it.
It's a legal question. When this person is in this gray zone
where these things are functioning and these things are not, does the
law consider this person to still be alive or dead? Right? You
could say maybe does your man on the street consider the person
to be alive or dead, but there's not a metaphysical reality of
death and we're trying to figure out does this person match it.
Okay, when you're way here at this end of the spectrum, then
yes, the person is definitely dead. It's the same thing about the
abortion question, when does life begin, right, is that a metaphysical reality
or is that a legal question? So in these gray areas it's
a legal question.
Like being guilty and innocent in the סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, if you're ruled
innocent by the court
you're innocent in other reality. Yes, but most people are intuitively think
about these questions of when does life begin and when is death
that there's a real reality out there that we're trying to find.
But there is with brain death, isn't there?
Well, there's a reality that the brain isn't working and other things
are working. Right. Right, they can see that. So the reality that
the brain is not,
doesn't say whether the person's alive.
Exactly, there's a reality to what the words brain death mean. But
whether that defines the person as dead if the heart is still
pumping, that's a legal question. Okay, so that is similar, I think,
a good example of that is this question about a shechted animal
that's still אבר מן החי eiver min hachai to a בן נח.
Ben Noach. Let's take a look now with those, right, with those
as words of introduction, let's take a look
now at the גמרא. Gemara. אמר זעירי, Amar Zeiri, so says
זעירי, Zeiri, נשברה מפרקת
ורוב בשר עמה, nishbera mafreket verov basar ima, if the backbone, the
spine was broken, the spinal cord is broken, and the, you know,
backbone doesn't mean the lower backbone. Do we have a word for
this? The part of the backbone that's like right up here?
Right. A nape?
The nape of the neck, I guess.
The nape.
What is a nape?
The nape is the part of the...
Anyway, that's the מפרקת. Mifreket. Okay, anyway, so if that part is
broken, that part of the bone and most of the of the
flesh that is with it, נבילה. nevela. The animal is a נבילה,
nevela, which means that even if you do a שחיטה shechita afterwards,
the animal is not a טרפה, treifa, it's a נבילה. nevela. Now
remember, I've been saying why do you not do מליקה melika from
the back? Because you'll make the animal a טרפה treifa before you
actually do the שחיטה. shechita. But he's going further, he's saying it's
not a טרפה, treifa, it's a נבילה. nevela. The basic difference of
נבילה nevela and טרפה treifa is does the animal cause טומאה tuma
if you act right afterwards. But how what's the halachic definition? A
טרפה treifa is an animal that was שחט shecht correctly but had
an injury that it couldn't live. A נבילה nevela is an animal
that was killed without שחיטה. shechita. So he is saying that if
you break it from the back of the neck with tear away
most of the flesh and the spine and you break through the
spine, it's a נבילה, nevela, which means you've already killed the animal,
not just you've given it a mortal injury, but you've killed it.
Halachically it's a נבילה. nevela. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara
does with this.
Where are we, one minute?
Is it still breathing?
Since it hasn't reached the קנה kane and it's not discussing that.
Right, it could've right? You have not reached the קנה, kane, you
have not reached the ושט, veshet, it's still breathing. And now you
see why this is relevant for the brain-death discussion. Okay, and it's
calling it a נבילה. nevela. Okay, but fatal injury is טרפה. treifa.
It's going that's it's going further, נבילה. nevela. That's exactly why this
is so relevant. Fatal injury is טרפה. treifa. That's what we would
have assumed but he's saying נבילה, nevela, which means it's halachically considered
to have been killed without an act of שחיטה. shechita. So this
sounds like he's
defining the backbone is broken and like you've ripped the flesh away.
Yeah, you tear through most of the flesh of the neck and
the back break the backbone. Okay, so let's take a look. אמר
רב חסדא אף אנן נמי תנינא. Amar Rav Chisda af anan nami
tanina. We touch simply. מלק בסכין מטמא בגדים בבית הבליעה. Malak b'sakin
metame begadim b'veit habliah. If you do מליקה melika with a knife,
right, which is a פסול מליקה, pasul melika, מליקה melika has to
be with the fingernail, but you did it so you did this
from the back of the neck. So then the animal it's not
a good מליקה melika and therefore what? So the animal is a
נבילה. nevela. מטמא בגדים בבית הבליעה Metame begadim b'veit habliah means a
כשר kasher bird when you swallow it, that's where it communicates its
טומאה tuma of נבילה nevela and it makes you and any clothes
you're wearing טמא. tame. But what's relevant for us is we see
that if you did a שחיטה shechita from the back of the
neck, which is what מליקה melika with a knife is, we don't
say the animal's a טרפה, treifa, we say it's a נבילה. nevela.
Why don't we say it's a טרפה? treifa? Why don't we say
fatal injury then you did the שחיטה? shechita? So therefore it's a
טרפה. treifa. We don't, we say it's a נבילה, nevela, which shows
that when you're coming from the back of the neck you have
killed it before you get to the קנה kane and the ושט,
veshet, killed it without a שחיטה, shechita, made it a נבילה. nevela.
So we're actually saying it's considered to have been killed.
For birds, okay, right. So we'll discuss how far you can take
this but you see the relevance. Okay, ואי אמרת טרפה הויא, V'ei
amart treifa havya, if you say that all you did was made
it a טרפה, treifa, fatal injury, מליקה זו היא שחיטתה. melika zu
hi shechitata. So when you're doing the מליקה, melika, you're meaning when
you're getting to the קנה kane and the ושט, veshet, you're doing
this with a knife. So you should that should be the שחיטה.
shechita. So okay, it's a טרפה, treifa, but at least it's a
טרפה, treifa, you did a good שחיטה. shechita. תהני ליה סכין וטהרה
מידי נבילה. Tehani lei sakin utahara midei nevela.
The knife should help to purify it from being a נבילה. nevela.
Meaning, since by the you're doing a knife from the back of
the neck, by the time you get to the קנה kane and
the ושט veshet you're שחט shechting it. So at least that act
of שחיטה shechita should say it's not a נבילה, nevela, it's a
טרפה, treifa, because you went through the back of the neck and
you gave it a fatal injury. But at least it's you שחט
shechted it. So at least let it be a טרפה treifa and
not have the טומאה, tuma, the impurity of a נבילה. nevela. So
we don't say that. So you see that when you're cutting through
the back of the neck before you get to the קנה kane
and the ושט veshet you are considered to have already killed the
animal.
Yeah, so one's also לכתחילה lechatchila and one's בדיעבד. bediavad. If you
do perfectly it's perfect because it does all the criteria and if
it just happens the other way it's not a way of wasting.
Right,
so you could try to say that maybe doing them in the
reverse order is a פסול שחיטה, psul shechita, but we haven't said
that yet. Until this point all we're considering is that you have
broken its neck which would have been made it a טרפה. treifa.
But here we're saying no, you actually see you've made it a
נבילה. nevela. So let's keep on going. So אמרי, Amri, so exactly
the answer might be what you're getting at, התם משום דלאו שחיטה
היא כלל. Hatam mishum d'lav shechita hi klal.
No, when you go from the back of the neck forget whether
cutting through makes it a טרפה treifa or נבילה. nevela. Even when
you get to the קנה kane and ושט veshet you're not doing
a שחיטה shechita act. Why not? מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, why not?
רב אמר מפני שהוא מחליד, Rav amar mipnei shehu machlid, because you
are burrowing. I'll get back to that. רבא אמר מפני שהוא דורס,
Rava amar mipnei shehu dores, because you are piercing. Now דורס dores
is easier, right? That was the question before. How do you do
מליקה? melika? Do you do it by piercing or do you can
you even do it by cutting? So רבא Rava is saying, no,
you have to do מליקה melika by piercing. So therefore when you
do it from the back of the neck, the reason the animal
is a נבילה nevela is because even when you get to the
קנה kane and ושט veshet you're not doing a שחיטה shechita act,
you're piercing it. Okay, that's רבא Rava's answer. Forget that you cut
through the spinal cord. If you do the act of מליקה melika
with a knife then you are doing an invalid שחיטה shechita because
you're doing it through stabbing and not through cutting. That's what רבא
Rava says. The other answer is מחליד. machlid. What is מחליד? machlid?
Burrowing. This is one of the פסולי שחיטה. psulei shechita. The normal
way this פסול שחיטה psul shechita is understood is when you start
between the סימנים, simanim, like you're burrowing your knife, tunneling your knife
between the סימנים, simanim, so here's my trachea and esophagus, right, I
should be cutting from the bottom up, but what I do is
I stick my knife between the two, I hide my knife essentially
in between the two סימנים, simanim, and I cut one and then
I let's say I cut the other. That's a פסול psul of
מחליד machlid of burrowing. Why is this the problem of מחליד? machlid?
So רש"י Rashi says the problem of מחליד machlid is because when
I cut through the backbone, the knife is now buried as it
were, burrowed between the backbone and the סימנים, simanim, right, so as
I'm continuing to cut, the bone sort of covers over the knife
that I just cut through, and therefore that's considered like the knife
is like hidden, not exposed, and it's sort of burrowing in inside
the neck, although it's not between the two סימנים, simanim, but it's
sort of burrowing in the neck. That's what רש"י Rashi says. תוספות
Tosafot says more simply, no, what מחליד machlid really refers to is
doing anything out of order. So the problem of going between the
two סימנים simanim is that you're not doing them in order, right,
you're not doing trachea and esophagus or whatever, you're not going from
bottom up, so here the problem is basically you're going from top
down not bottom up.
That's an independent problem. Right. So the basic way we're answering is
we try to say I'll prove to you that when you cut
through the back of the neck you've made the animal a נבילה.
neveila. How? Because we say that if you did מליקה melika with
a knife, it's a נבילה. neveila. So says no, that's not because
you went necessarily because it's considered killed by the time you get
through the back of the neck, that's because when you even get
to the trachea and esophagus, you're not doing a good שחיטה. shechita.
Why not? Either because you're stabbing and not cutting, or because you're
doing this problem of burrowing, it's buried, it's either the reverse order,
it's buried underneath the bone, that's the problem. Okay, but you can't
prove that as soon as you get through the back of the
neck it's considered a נבילה. neveila.
So now the גמרא Gemara just clarifies this, where were we, משום
דורס. mishum dorays. מאן דאמר משום מחליד מאי טעמא לא אמר משום
דורס? man de-amar mishum machlid mai ta'ama lo amar mishum dorays? The
one that says the problem is burrowing, why didn't he say the
problem is pressure? Pressure here means anything that's not the sharpness of
the cutting, so it's the stabbing, it's not as opposed to the
pressure. קסבר מוליך ומביא במליקה כשר kasavar molich u-mavi bi-melika kasher because
he said look, I think it's possible to do מליקה melika with
the back and forth motion, so I'm not going to say that
every מליקה melika is necessarily the problem of pressure or stabbing. You
could in theory be doing this thing with the knife from the
back of the neck with a back and forth motion. ומאן דאמר
משום דורס מאי טעמא לא אמר משום מחליד? u-man de-amar mishum dorays
mai ta'ama lo amar mishum machlid? The one that says the problem
is
stabbing, why didn't he say the problem is this burrowing when you
go from the back of the neck? אמר לך, amar lach, he'll
tell you, חלדה היכי דמי? chaluda heichi dami? No, what's the case
of burrowing? כחולדה kechulda like a weasel הדרה בעיקרי הבתים hadara be-ikrei
ha-batim that lives like underneath the floor of your house.
דמיכסיא demichasya הכא hacha that is hidden.
הא הכא מיגליא, ha hacha migalya, it's exposed, which means it's not
like even if when you cut through the back, even though it's
true it gets underneath the bone that it cuts through, still basically
it's going from the outside in and it's not like
you started through the side of the neck and through covering up
the knife and burrowing the knife into the neck. You started with
the knife with a simple cut from the outside in, so that's
not a problem. The burrowing is only when you go into the
middle of the neck, you essentially hide the knife in the neck
and start your cutting there. Okay, so that's the question about how
to define the problem. But we're still back to our issue, which
is the claim is that as soon as you cut through the
back of the neck, it's a נבילה, neveila, can we prove it
from the fact that מליקה melika makes an animal a נבילה neveila
when done incorrectly? No, מליקה melika has other problems why it makes
the animal a נבילה. neveila. Because it's not a good שחיטה, shechita,
because either it's stabbing and not cutting or it's this problem called
מחליד, machlid, that's what's in מליקה melika is, that doesn't prove that
when you get through the back of the neck that you've made
the animal a נבילה. neveila. But let's keep on going because the
גמרא Gemara is not done. אמר רבא, amar Rava, אי קשיא לי
הא קשיא לי. i kashya li ha kashya li. If I've got
a question about this statement, here's my question. וכי מתה עומד ומליק?
vechi mesa omayd u-molayk? Which says look, he says I can't accept
that by the time you get through the back of the neck
the animal's already considered a נבילה, neveila, why not? Because then when
you finish you do the act of מליקה, melika, you get to
the trachea and esophagus, you're now doing מליקה melika on a bird
that is halakhically considered to be dead or at least a נבילה,
neveila, but it's actually very important that he uses the word מתה
mesa here, right, we've shifted from נבילה neveila to מתה, mesa, which
נבילה neveila might have implied מתה mesa but here it's obviously based
on my introduction significant that he actually uses the word מתה. mesa.
So how could you be doing מליקה melika on an animal that's
already dead? Why would that be כשר? kasher? If by the time
you got to the trachea and esophagus halakhically this animal's considered dead.
So וכי מתה עומד ומליק? vechi mesa omayd u-molayk? So אמר ליה
אביי, amar lay Abbaye, so אביי Abbaye says to him, ותקשי לך
עולת העוף vetikshei lach olat ha-of דבעיא שני סימנים. de-baya shenei simanim.
How about a normal bird sacrifice that you have to cut both
the trachea and esophagus, even though normal שחיטה shechita of a bird
is only one is required. וכי מתה עומד ומליק? vechi mesa omayd
u-molayk? Why are you cutting the other סימן siman if it's already
dead after one סימן? siman? Are you doing מליקה melika on an
animal that's already dead? So the basic thing אביי Abbaye is saying
is yeah, that's part of the חידוש chiddush of מליקה melika is
that you do it even though halakhically you've killed the animal in
the process. that's before you're done. So אמר ליה, Amar Leh, so
רבא Rava said back to him, no. התם כדי לקיים בה מצוות
הבדלה. Hasam kedei lekayem bah mitzvas havdalah. There when you שחט shecht
the other סימן, siman, it's not to sort of kill it and
consider the act of מליקה, melikah, it's because the תורה Torah says
by a bird sacrifice it says that והבדיל vehivdil
it says ושיסע veshisah no ולא יבדיל velo yavdil by חטאת. chatas.
Anyway, by a bird עולה olah you're supposed to be מבדיל, mavdil,
you're supposed to separate the head from the body. So the reason
you cut the other סימן siman is you're right, you're not cutting
it as a שחיטה shechita type of an act, you're cutting it
just to finish the cutting through of the head. You are cutting
a dead animal. That doesn't bother me. That's not to do the
מליקה melikah per se, that's just to separate the head from the
body.
Right, you're not trying to kill it further, you're just trying to
cut the skin further. So אי הכי ei hachi says the גמרא,
Gemara, if that's true, אורנמי, ornami, so you should cut the actual
skin, outer skin of the animal's neck if you're trying to just
sever the head. No. כל המעכב בשחיטה מעכב בהבדלה. Kol ham'akev bishchita
m'akev behavdala. Anything that prevents it from being שחיטה, shchita, anything that's
involved in the שחיטה shchita like the trachea or the esophagus, that's
what's required to do to consider it to be severing the head.
וכל שאינו מעכב בשחיטה, Vechol she'eino m'akev bishchita, something that is not
prevent a valid שחיטה, shchita, meaning the outside skin of the neck,
אינו מעכב בהבדלה, eino m'akev behavdala, is not something that is a
problem in terms of this requirement of severing the head. So the
גמרא Gemara says one minute, אמיות סימנים לרבנן דלא מעכב בשחיטה מעכב
בהבדלה? amiyut simanim lerabbanan delo m'akev bishchita m'akev behavdala? The Rabbis say,
right, there's a question about whether you have to do completely sever
the entire trachea and esophagus or just רוב rov of it for
this case of the bird. So that case of the minority of
the סימן siman is again not a problem for שחיטה. shchita. For
שחיטה shchita it's not required, you only have to do the majority
of the סימן. siman. And the Rabbis say that you do have
to completely cut through the trachea and esophagus by this bird עולה
olah to sever it. So you see that something that is not
a שחיטה shchita problem but is part of the severing and מעכב
בהבדלה. m'akev behavdala. אלא אימא, Ella eima, okay so let's rephrase it.
כל שישנו בשחיטה ישנו בהבדלה. Kol sheyeshno bishchita yeshno behavdala. Anything that
is part of the שחיטה shchita act, could be part of the
שחיטה shchita act, whether it's trachea, the esophagus, any part of the
trachea and esophagus, those are the things that have to be severed
for the requirement to sever the head of the bird of the
עולה olah from the body. וכל שאינו בשחיטה, Vechol she'eino bishchita, things
that are not part of the שחיטה shchita act at all, like
the outer skin of the animal, אינו בהבדלה, eino behavdala, is not
part of the act of separating. But now we're still back to
the question. Okay, you've explained to me why I can cut the
second סימן siman of the bird, it's not that the bird is
already dead, it doesn't matter the bird is already dead, it's because
I have to sever the head. But we're back to רבא's Rava
question, if you consider the bird dead by the time you get
through the back of the neck and the spinal cord, how are
you doing מליקה melikah on a dead bird, right? What sense does
that make that the act of מליקה melikah is on a bird
that's already dead? So let's just read the answer and then we'll
talk a minute about the brain dead issue. מכל מקום קשיא, mikol
makom kashya, so nevertheless this is difficult. So אמר רבא, Amar Rava,
right, how are you doing מליקה melikah on a dead bird? אמר
רבא אימא וכן הוא עושה. Amar Rava eima vechen hu oseh.
We have to say that this is how מליקה melikah is done
based on this question, rather than reject the idea the bird is
a נבילה, neveilah, we're going to revise our understanding of what the
act of מליקה melikah is. And this has to be how we
understand the act of מליקה. melikah. חותך שדרה
ומפרקת, Chotech shidrah umifrekes, you break through basically the spinal cord and
the nape of the neck, בלא רוב בשר, belo rov basar, but
you do not sever the most of the flesh around it. Were
you to sever most of the flesh around it you would make
it a נבילה. neveilah. So you basically have to get to the
trachea and the esophagus by cutting through the back of the neck
without cutting away most without severing most of the skin.
You have
to right, a more precision piercing, but you do have to avoid
making the bird a נבילה. neveilah. So we are not rejecting the
we are embracing the idea that if you break through the spinal
cord and most of the flesh you have made it a נבילה,
neveilah, and therefore your שחיטה shchita would not your מליקה melikah would
not be valid. The only way to make the מליקה melikah valid
is to keep the bird essentially halachically alive till you get to
the trachea and the esophagus.
The flesh around and that's in the right of the spinal cord?
Yeah, presumably, yeah.
Or how does that make a bird any more dead
than cutting through the spinal cord? Yeah, I'm not exactly sure about
that either. So those are good questions. So let me actually let
me just say two things.
First of all, and just before you go to the things I
just can you just help us understand what's the difference between מיתה,
meisa, נבילה, neveilah, and טריפה? treifa?
Well, that's what the discussion will be. It just has to be
one סימן siman *siman* from the מליקה *melikah*.
Which one? Either, man, either one,
either one.
So I want to say first of all one thing to clarify
what רש"י *Rashi* takes great pains to spell out, which is רש"י
*Rashi* says "And why is it better now? I mean, I understand
that it’s and you don't want to make it a נבלה neveilah
*neveilah* and then kill it because it’s already dead, halachically or it’s
already a נבלה neveilah *neveilah*. But why is it better now? Now
it’s a טרפה *treifah* by the time you kill it, so why
is that okay? Why is that kosher?" So רש"י *Rashi* says that’s
not a conceptual problem because he says every שחיטה *shechitah* is that
way. Exactly. Every שחיטה *shechitah*, if I were to stop a second
before I finish the act of שחיטה *shechitah*, I’ve already made it
a טרפה *treifah*. Part of שחיטה *shechitah* is killing it! So the
fact that so the fact that I’m making it a
טרפה *treifah*, giving it a mortal wound before I finish the act,
that’s not a problem. The problem is if I’ve actually killed it
before I finish the act, then how can you say I’m doing
a שחיטה *shechitah* or a מליקה *melikah* on an animal that’s already
נבלה neveilah, *neveilah*? So now let’s talk about the the question about
the relevance of this statement. So first to respond to David’s point.
So again, what’s a טרפה *treifah*? טרפה *treifah* is an animal that
is considered alive but mortally wounded. Okay. נבלה neveilah. *neveilah* normally we
understand is an animal that is actually dead without without the act,
a proper act of שחיטה *shechitah*. So נבלה neveilah, *neveilah* could be
an animal that died of old age, נבלה neveilah, *neveilah* could be
an animal that you actually used a gun to kill, and נבלה
neveilah *neveilah* could be an animal that you
stabbed, right, killed by another נבלה neveilah. *neveilah* is a corpse of
an animal without a שחיטה *shechitah*, okay, but it’s considered normally we
assume it means a dead animal. That’s what a נבלה *neveilah* is.
Now the question as I started in the beginning phrase, is that
definition the same as the the idea, the word dead, dead. Notice
of course that the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* uses these phrases. It says
starts by saying it’s a נבלה *neveilah* and then when רבא *Rava*
says "Are you going to kill an animal that’s a מתה mesa.
*meisah*, that’s a dead animal?" Similarly, when the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* talks
about a bird, right, remember what it said? It said "Well, I
don't understand," said אביי *Abaye*, "when you cut one סימן siman *siman*,
are you cutting a bird that’s already a מתה mesa. *meisah*?" Right?
That was אביי *Abaye*'s statement. He says he says after one certain
was אביי *Abaye*'s statement, וכי מתה mesa עומד ומושחט *v'chi
meisah omeid umoshchet* right, סיפא דמתה *seifa demesiah*. Now that’s a little
strange, right? Because normally if you’ve got to kill two סימנים simanim.
*simanim* by a בהמה *beheimah* and one סימן *siman* by a bird,
presumably the difference is what constitutes an act of שחיטה *shechitah*. Not
that by a cow we’re saying if I cut one סימן *siman*
by a cow we’re going to say it’s alive, but by a
bird we’re going to say it’s dead. I might say that the
bird is שחטד *shechted* and the cow isn’t שחטד *shechted* yet. So
again the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* has a little bit of like liberal
use of the word מתה *meisah* and does it really mean מתה
*meisah* as a definition of death? Or or is it really saying
the question of is it שחטד *shechted*? So regarding the issue of
נבלה *neveilah*, let’s go to that. If you can see from here
why this could be relevant for people trying to establish a concept
of brain death. The idea of how do you try to define
brain death in הלכה *halacha*, where do you get that concept in
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*? There are basically two approaches. One which is,
I would say the easier approach, is not to emphasize the idea
of brain death per se, but what happens at brain death? At
brain death the body loses the autonomous ability to
breathe. Okay, the breathing is continued by a machine that allows the
heart to keep on pumping and so on. But it loses the
autonomous ability to breathe at brain death. So some people try to
say "We're not defining brain death," but if you look at the
גמרות *Gemaros* that talk about death, they always are talking about breathing
and testing for breathing. So what we're really saying is if the
body doesn't can’t breathe on its own, then due to a system
failure not because let’s say there’s a local problem, but then that’s
death. Death is the inability for autonomous breathing. Other approaches that’s the
one that’s easier to substantiate based on sources in the גמרא *Gemara*.
Other approaches say "No, no, no, there’s a brain death is a
per se definition of death." Where do you see that in the
גמרא *Gemara*? So one place they turn to is this. Here's an
animal with its head cut, severed. It still has its trachea and
esophagus. Nobody has said it’s not breathing, nobody has said blood isn't
going through it. But because the spinal cord is cut and essentially
the the brain is not communicating with the rest of the body,
so you see that therefore it is defined as death. And therefore
we can use this as a definition of death. Now the problem
with that is, I mean I'm all for that in principle, but
I'll just point out the logic problem. One is the question that
James raised. And therefore why if you don't do most of the
flesh is it okay? I mean you still severed the spinal cord,
right? So
A, is that really what's going on in terms of the גמרא
*Gemara*'s idea? Number two is the question which is at the core
for us, is נבלה *neveilah* the same as מתה *meisah*? The גמרא
*Gemara* here used them interchangeably. But when the רמב"ם *Rambam* quotes this
הלכה *halacha*, the רמב"ם *Rambam* says, get this, he says "if you
broke רוב בשר rov basar המפרקת *rov basar hamaphreket*, the בהמה *beheimah*
is a נבלה *neveilah* אף על פי שלא מתה *af al pi
shelo meisah* or something like that." Or okay let me actually quote
the language of the רמב"ם *Rambam* because I’m I don't think I'm
doing it precisely. So hold on a minute.
Let me just quote it let’s see.
Which obviously shows that something could be considered נבלה like its death,
or maybe the הרמב"ם Rambam isn't as explicit. He might say הרי
היא כמתה. harei hi kemesa. But he has some language which,
you know, which
sort of separates the concept of נבלה from the strict definition of
death. Oh yeah. בהמה או חיה טמאה
שנשחטה אינה מטמאה משום נבלה כל זמן שהיא מפרכסת, beheimah
o chayah temei'ah
shenishchatah einah metamei mishum neveilah kol zman shehi mefarcheres, wait no, עד
שתמות. ad shetamus. Wait
a minute. Yeah, oh no,
so it wasn't as explicit. It was,
here's what he said: וכן אם קרעה מגבה או שנשברה מפרקת ורוב
בשר עמה, vechein im kar'ah migavah o shenishberah mofrekes verov basar imah,
you broke its backbone or whatever, and or the back of the
neck and most of the flesh, הרי זו כנבלה לכל דבר. harei
zo kineveilah lechol davar.
So actually no, it wasn't nearly as explicit as I thought. That
would really have been a problem for that camp. But he says
it is like a נבלה for all things. So the point is,
he doesn't even say it is a נבלה, he just says it's
like a נבלה. Okay. Anyway, so that really though is at the
heart of the question. The heart of the question here is is
that when we say נבלה, does that mean definition of death? And
again, the thing to note is that the גמרא, for example, by
birds, says, oh, if you שחט shecht one סימן it's already dead.
Are you going to שחט shecht an animal that's dead? And it's
hard to imagine, as I said, that the גמרא really thinks that,
you know, that the bird is dead, but the animal is not
yet dead. Right? The difference between one סימן and two סימנים. So
this gets back to the question I asked earlier, which is, you
know, is there independent definitions of what does it mean to be
שחט, shechted, what does it mean to be a נבלה, and what
does it mean to be dead? A נבלה could be an animal
that's basically like, you know, that's
effectively dead, but not yet fully dead. You know, this gray area,
exactly this gray area that we're talking about, right? So maybe this
gray area where something is effectively dead but the systems have not
finished like running their course, you know, and petering out, maybe that's
enough for נבלה. Maybe that's not yet a מתה. Maybe something could
be a שחוטה shechutah without yet being a מתה. So the exact
question about is this relevant for definitions of death is not at
all clear from this גמרא, but what needs to be noted is
number one, the idea of the broken back of the neck is
somewhat analogous to a concept of brain death, although not exactly as
we said רוב בשר doesn't seem directly relevant, and number two, the
point as that the גמרא literally applies the term of מתה here,
although it's not so clear it really means it literally. Okay.